"How to Improve Your Heart Rate Variability"
Everyone feel for your pulse.
Hold out your hand, thumb up,
and feel for the knobby bone
at the top of your wrist.
Okay, now,
slide your hand down
and across the front
of your wrist.
Feel those, like,
strands of spaghetti?
Those are the tendons
in your wrist.
If you press lightly
between the knobby bone
and that first tendon,
you should feel your pulse.
Got it?
Okay,
now what we're going to do
is feel what happens
to our pulse
when we take a deep breath.
We're going to try it twice.
Try to feel what happens
to your pulse when you inhale
and when you exhale.
All right, here we go,
slow inhale.
(inhales)
Slow exhale.
(exhales)
One more time.
In.
Out.
What happened when you
breathed in and breathed out?
You should have felt your pulse
speed up when you inhaled
and slow down
when you exhaled.
That's called
heart rate variability,
a measure of the control
our vagus nerve has
over our heart.
And it's a good thing.
A healthy heart
is not a metronome.
Low heart rate variability
predicts greater risk
of heart disease and death
from several causes.
High-risk patients with
low variability in heart rate
have twice the risk
of dying prematurely.
Is there anything we can do
to positively impact
heart rate variability?
Voluntary slow breathing,
at about six breaths per minute,
is a technique that's been used
for thousands of years
as an essential part
of many meditative
and relaxation practices.
It can benefit several heart
rate variability parameters,
offering a low-tech,
low-cost technique.
Speaking of low-tech, low-cost:
What about exercise?
Aerobic training
at least twice a week
positively influences
heart nerve control.
What about what we eat?
Those eating plant-based diets
have better
overall heart rate variability.
Vegetarians, for example,
don't tend to have only
better blood pressure,
cholesterol, triglycerides,
and blood sugars,
they also have
better heart rate variability.
The vagus nerve toning effects
of plant-based diets
may help explain part of
their cardioprotective effect.
Any plants in particular?
While no significant association
was seen
between heart rate
variability measures
and the intake of fruits
and vegetables in general,
the consumption
of green leafy vegetables
seems to stand out,
perhaps helping to explain
why eating just a half serving
of greens a day
may cut our risk
of having a heart attack
by up to 67 percent!